Ruben E. Reina Papers Mss.Ms.Coll.67 Mss.Ms.Coll.67
American Philosophical Society
Ruben E. Reina Papers
1951-2004
Mss.Ms.Coll.67
American Philosophical Society
80.0 Linear feet
80 linear feet.
The Reina Papers contain the professional papers of cultural anthropologist Ruben E. Reina (1924- ). Reina is an emeritus professor of anthropology and curator of ethnology who taught at the University of Pennsylvania and worked at that institution’s University Museum of Archeology and Anthropology from 1957-1990. Broadly interested in modern and historical cultures of Central America, South America, and Spain, he is most widely known for his contributions to the study of the culture and peoples of Guatemala. The collection contains Reina’s correspondence, administrative records, teaching materials, research notes, subject files, and written works from his career. Of particular interest are the notes from his fieldwork in Guatemala, Argentina, Spain, and Puerto Rico. A further significant component of the papers is the records of the Hispanic-Latin American Research Project. Reina served as director of the long-term project (1967-1988), during which a team of scholars compiled thousands of pages of Spanish colonial materials from the Archivo General de Indias (AGI) in Seville, Spain and Archivos General de Centro America (AGCA) in Guatemala. The Reina Papers serve as a vital storehouse of this important historical material.
Reina, Ruben E.
Scope and Contents note
SERIES I. AUDIENCIA DE GUATEMALA
This series includes notes and photocopies of documents relating to the Audiencia de Guatemala, the first 100 years after the Spanish Conquest.The original documents are housed in the Archivos General de Indias (AGI) in Seville, and allow for the study of both Spanish and Mayan people as they interacted during the sixteenth century. After a period of conquest and pacification, the Spanish began a time of colonization and consolidation in the region. The Hispanic-Latin American Research Project, under the direction of Ruben Reina, began studying this material in 1967.
Subseries A. Microfilm
This microfilm consists of images of approximately 70,000 pages of documents (129 microfilm rolls) for the first one hundred years after the conquest in 1524. Microfilm reels are housed with the rest of the APS microfilm as Film #1337.
Subseries B. Transcriptions
These 5 x 8 card files are transcriptions of documents in the Archivos General de Indias, Seville, Spain (AGI), 1509-1784. Under the sponsorship of the American Philosophical Society and other funding, from 1965 to 1972, Ruben E. Reina and Dr. Alfredo Jimenez of the University of Sevilla directed the selection and transcriptions of document related to the first one hundred years after the Conquest (1524).
The 5 x 8 cards usually contain a transcription of the entire document, though when parts have been omitted they are replaced either with ellipses (…) or with summaries by the people (copistas) who transcribed the documents. Each transcription contains a page number at the top and the source (AGI) at the bottom. In the text the page (folio) # is indicated. These transcriptions are part of the collection (full document) on microfilm (see microfilm collection APS by R. E. Reina and Edward O’Flaherty).
The series also includes classification of data from transcribed documents (AGI) by cultural categories. See Peter Murdock's outline of cultural material based on transcribed documents. Participants in this project included Reina and Rosa Portell, a research assistant at the University. The project was interrupted in late 1970.
The cards are arranged chronologically, with tabs dividing each year and document. Restrictions: Permission from the AGI is necessary for publication.
Subseries C. Project History
This subseries consists of material produced and gathered by Ruben Reina, Father Edward O'Flaherty, and others in their research. The material includes reports; data compilation; guides to the Archivos General de Indias (AGI) in Seville, Spain and the Archivos General de Centro America (AGCA) in Guatemala; research notes of the project team; and copies of published sources consulted during the project. The series includes Edward O'Flaherty's notes for his work "Institutionalization of the Catholic Church: The Case of Colonial Guatemala."
SERIES II. PETEN
The Peten Ethnohistory material consists of photocopies of documents from local community archives and the Archivo General de Centroamerica relating to the Peten department, or region, of Guatemala. The material dates from the 15th century through 1899. Reina copied the material with portable photocopy and photographic equipment under poor conditions. The collection also includes transcriptions of material relating to Guatemala during the Spanish Conquest.
Subseries A. Encomiendas y Tierras
This series consists of photocopies of material from the Archivo General de Centro America (AGCA) in Guatemala from 1586-1691 that are not available in the Archivo General de Indias (AGI) in Seville. The copies were collected during the summer of 1970 by Ruben E. Reina and Salvador Rodriguez. Each document has the call number from the AGCA. Some documents may cover a number of years. All materials are in the Spanish language unless indicated as Maya language.
Subseries B. Libros de Cofradias
This portion of the collection includes the locations of the encomenderos listed by pueblos (communities) for the Highland region of Guatemala.
Lista de Autoridades Espanolas - 100 anos despues de la Conquista Lista de Autoridades y sus Jurisdiciones –Guatemala: 1526 –1570 Tasaciones de 1548–1549 Lista de Encomendero por Pueblos Jurisdicion de Santiago Lista de Encomenderos - Padron Ciudad Guaemala -1604. Lista de Gobernadores de Guatemala en el Siglo XVI (58 pages).
Subseries C. Ethnohistorical Data
Photocopies and photographs of documents from local community archives, oral histories, and AGCA. (Portable photocopy and photographic equipment used under poor conditions).
Subseries D. Peten Court Records
The Peten Court Records consist of photocopies of documents from the Archivo General de Centroamerica in Guatemala. The records are arranged by offense. These copies have acquired particular significance as the original documents were destroyed by a city flood in the 1980s.
Subseries E. Transcriptions
Transcriptions 5 x 8 cards - transcriptions of the Peten Court Records from the Archivo General de Centroamerica in Guatemala. The cards were prepared by student assistants throughout several years. Not all documents have been verified for accuracy. Each card has the identification number of the document at the upper left.
SERIES III. CHINAUTLA AND CHINAUTLA-RELATED
This series consists of material relating to the Chinautla region and neighboring areas of Guatemala. Ruben Reina studied the Chinautlecos extensively throughout his career. He discovered that, despite over 400 years of interaction with the Spanish and their proximity to a large city, the Pokomam-speaking people retained their own distinctive identity, persevering with a culture neither purely Maya nor purely Spanish. Reina's field work studying the Chinautlecos resulted in at least two major works--his doctoral dissertation, "Chinautla, a Guatemalan Indian Community: A Study in the Relationship of Community Culture and National Change." (University of North Carolina, 1957); and an ethnography, The Law of the Saints: A Pokomam Pueblo and its Community Culture (Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1966). This series contains both copies of historical documents from the Archivo Generale de Centro America (AGCA) (primarily from the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries) and field work from the 1970s and 1980s, including transcripts of interviews.
Subseries A. Chinautla
This subseries includes copies of documents from the Archivo Generale de Centro America pertaining to Chinautla, Guatemala and its people.
Subseries B. Chinautla-Related
This subseries consists of copies of documents from the Archivo Generale de Centro America that pertain to other communities related to Chinautla.
SERIES IV. SACAPULAS
This series consists of notes and photocopies of documents relating to the Sacapulas region of Guatemala. Included are copies of priests' records, Mayan language material including a Mayan dictionary, and other documents from the Archivos General de Centro America (AGCA).
SERIES V. ZUNIL
This series consists of notes and photocopies of documents relating to the Zunil people of Guatemala. In 1969, Ruben Reina hired a local Zunil man, Francisco Quiej, to collect material--legends and stories--from the monolingual elders of Zunil. Quiej recorded the interviews, then translated the accounts from their original Quiche in to Spanish. Via a local priest, Quiej sent the transcripts to Reina. The original recordings no longer exist, but the surviving transcripts serve as an important historical record of the beliefs and experiences of a native Central American people. Included are legends, religious texts, and interviews with and biographies of community members.
SERIES VI. SUBJECT FILES
Files of articles, notes, student work, and other materials not easily classified as they relate to more than one project. These include reports to the National Science Foundation and materials relating to courses taught by Ruben E. Reina at the University of Pennsylvania.
SERIES VII. CORRESPONDENCE
Correspondence of Ruben E. Reina with colleagues. The surviving letters, while representing a sample of letters received and written during Reina's career, shed light on his academic endeavors, including insight in to his time at the University of Pennsylvania, fieldwork, records of funding for his research, and requests for reprints from other scholars for his works. The letters are organized chronologically. Some letters are written in Spanish.
SERIES VIII. WORKS BY REINA
This series contains works by Ruben E. Reina. It includes manuscript versions of Reina's Master of Arts and Ph.D. theses, material related to all of Reina's books, and various chapters and journal articles. Also, there are numerous folders relating to a collaborative project undertaken by Reina in 1987 with several of his graduate students--Greta Borie, Charles Ward, Robert Maxwell, and John Lawrence. The project sought to follow up on Reina's groundbreaking ethnography on the Chinaulta by reconstructing eighteenth-century Santa Cruz Chinautla through Cuenta y Padron documents.
SERIES IX. WORKS BY OTHERS
This series includes manuscripts of works by former students of Ruben E. Reina at the University of Pennsylvania--Greta Borie, Robert Maxwell, William Rust, and P. A. Urban.
SERIES X. PUERTO RICAN MARKETS
Card files of notes on Puerto Rican Markets, 1956-1957, arranged by cultural categories. The series consists of three 5 x 8 card file boxes. Reina began this project at the University of Puerto Rico as the result of a student's participation in a seminar for ethnographic fieldwork. Reina and the students in training visited the markets, taking notes and transcribing them. No publication as yet has resulted from the work.
SERIES XI. PHOTOGRAPHS
This series includes photographs taken by Ruben E. Reina during his fieldwork in Guatemala and during travels in Spain, Portugal, Bolivia, Peru, Morocco, and Iran. It consists of over 5,000 color slides, black and white silver gelatin photographs, black and white contact prints, negatives, watercolor paintings, and sketches of Maya Indians of the central highlands and lowlands of Guatemala from 1951-1991. Ethnographic images were taken by Reina while conducting field work in Flores, Peten, Chinautla, Chichicastenango, Zunil, Antigua, and Huehuetenango. Primarily Pokomam Indians at market places, making pottery, weaving, ceremonial dancing, farming, candle-making, types of dwellings, and portraits in native attire. Of particular interest are depictions of Holy Week and Easter celebrations in the lowlands of Antigua, 1955-1959.
SERIES XII. PAINTINGS
This series includes paintings by Ruben E. Reina. Paintings include portraits of people in Guatemala and scenes of people in the midst of daily tasks. Reina’s colorful oversize paintings, 1990-2000, illustrate the ritual of the skulls, weaving, pottery, salt producing, and asking for rain. Reference notes on each image (i.e. 61-14-288) refer to year of the field work, cultural category, and number of print.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Ruben E. Reina.
Related Archival Materials note
APS possesses the papers of a few of Ruben Reina's colleagues in the department of anthropology at the University of Pennsylvania. See also the papers of Ward Goodenough ( Mss.Ms.Coll.120), Dell Hymes ( Mss.Ms.Coll.55), and Anthony Wallace ( Mss.Ms.Coll.64).
Biographical/Historical note
Ruben E. Reina (1924- ) is a cultural anthropologist and emeritus professor of anthropology and curator of ethnology who taught at the University of Pennsylvania and worked at that institution’s University Museum of Archeology and Anthropology from 1957-1990.
Broadly interested in modern and historical cultures of Central America, South America, and Spain, Reina is most widely known for his contributions to the study of the culture and peoples of Guatemala. His research interests include: the study of cultural change; ethnographic and ethnohistorical studies; contemporary and traditional Maya Indians; and modern Latin American peoples, peasants, and urban communities. Throughout the course of his career, Reina undertook extensive fieldwork in Guatemala, Argentina, Spain, and Puerto Rico. Widely traveled, he also pursued additional field activities in Mexico, Brazil, Guyana, Turkey, Iran, Morocco, Alaska, the Southwestern United States, Peru, Bolivia, and Scotland. In addition to teaching in the Department of Anthropology at Penn, Reina held a long-time appointment as a curator for the University Museum of Archeology and Anthropology.
Ruben E. Reina was born in Huinca Renenco, Cordoba Province, Argentina on December 5, 1924. His parents were Domingo and Margarita (Vidala) Reina. After graduating from a Bachiller in Argentina (1945-1947), and briefly studying geology at the Universidad de Cordoba (1947), he moved to the United States to further his education.
Reina earned a bachelor of arts degree in sociology and anthropology from the University of Michigan in 1950, and a master of arts degree in sociology and anthropology, with an emphasis on rural sociology, from Michigan State University in 1951. He followed these achievements in 1957 by being awarded a Ph.D. from the University of North Carolina. Reina has the distinction of being the first person to graduate from that university with a Ph.D. in anthropology.
After early teaching stints at the Women’s College at the University of North Carolina as an instructor in sociology and at the University of Puerto Rico as an assistant professor of anthropology, Reina accepted two appointments at the University of Pennsylvania. In 1957, he was appointed to an assistant professorship in the Department of Anthropology and to an assistant curatorship at the University Museum. This began more than three decades-worth of association with the prestigious Ivy League university. In 1962, after five years of service, Reina earned a promotion to associate professor and associate curator. A further five years at Penn saw him establish himself as a full professor and curator.
During this time, Reina began his association with the Hispanic-Latin American Research Project. The project began in 1967 and sought to compile source material from distant Spanish and Latin American archival and manuscript repositories and make them more easily available to scholars in the United States. Reina served as director of the project and led a team compiling information on “Society and Culture in Sixteenth-Century Guatemala.” The team culled thousands of pages of materials from the Archivo General de Indias (AGI) in Seville, Spain and Archivos General de Centro America (AGCA) in Guatemala. The project, which lasted the better part of twenty years, was funded in-part by the American Philosophical Society; its findings are part of the Reina Papers.
After firmly establishing himself as a full professor at Penn, Reina was awarded an honorary degree by the university, having been granted a master of arts, honoris causa, in 1971. Reina taught full-time at the university until 1990, when he achieved emeritus status, both as a professor and curator.
As curator for the University Museum, Reina directed several exhibitions including: “The Traditional Textiles of the Mayan People of Guatemala” (1971); “The Traditional Potters of Guatemala” (with Robert Hill) (1978); and, “The Gift of Birds: Featherwork of Native South American Peoples” (1991). This final exhibition explored "featherwork as a medium through which to examine the aesthetic, religious, and social values of the native South American peoples."
During his tenure at Penn, Reina performed several administrative functions, serving as: chairman of the undergraduate program in anthropology (1960-1966); acting assistant chairman of the department of anthropology (1966); chairman of the department of anthropology (1971-1976); and curator of the Loren Eiseley seminar and library (1982-1984).
In addition to teaching at the University of Pennsylvania, Reina also taught as a visiting professor at Bryn Mawr College (1969) and Colorado College (1976, 1978).
Reina’s major publications include: Chinautla, A Guatemalan Indian Community: A Study in the Relationship of Community Culture and National Change (1960); Entrepreneurship in Argentine Culture (with Thomas Cochran) (1962); The Law of the Saints: A Pokomam Pueblo and Its Community Culture (1967); Parana: Social Boundaries in an Argentine City (1973); The Traditional Pottery of Guatemala (with Robert Hill) (1978); and, Shadows: A Mayan Way of Knowing (1984).
Reina married Betty Burton on September 1, 1951. The couple has three sons: Mark, Randall, and Roger. In addition to his achievements in academics, Reina is an accomplished artist, with skills in oil, watercolor, acrylic, and ink media. Several of his pieces have been shown publicly, and are included in the Reina Papers at APS.
Chay, Francisco Quiej; Dyson, Robert H.; Eiseley, Loren C., 1907-1977; Gillin, John P., (John Philip), 1907-1973; Hispanic-Latin American Research Project.; Honigmann, John Joseph; Jimenez Nunez, Alfredo; O’Flaherty, Edward; University of Pennsylvania-Department of Anthropology; University of Pennsylvania. University Museum; Wallace, Anthony F. C., 1923-; Chinautla (Guatemala); Contact prints; Gelatin silver prints; Indians of Central America--Guatemala--Antigua Region; Indians of Central America--Guatemala--Atitlan, Lake, Region; Indians of Central America--Guatemala--Chinautla; Indians of Central America--Guatemala--Huehuetenango (Dept.); Indians of Central America--Guatemala--Languages; Indians of Central America--Guatemala--Peten (Dept.); Indians of Central America--Guatemala--Quezaltenango (Dept.); Mayan languages; Mayas--Guatemala--Social life and customs; Negatives; Pokomam Indians--Social life and customs; Prints--Color; Slides.; Watercolors
- Series I. Audiencia de Guatemala, Bulk, 1526-1839; 1526-1980, Bulk 1526-1839 (Microfiche 1337, Box 1-28.5)
  Series I. Audiencia de Guatemala
  This series includes notes and photocopies of documents relating to the Audiencia de Guatemala, the first 100 years after the Spanish Conquest.The original documents are housed in the Archivos General de Indias (AGI) in Seville, and allow for the study of both Spanish and Mayan people as they interacted during the sixteenth century. After a period of conquest and pacification, the Spanish began a time of colonization and consolidation in the region. The Hispanic-Latin American Research Project, under the direction of Ruben Reina, began studying this material in 1967.
  - Subseries A. Microfilm (Microfiche 1337)
    Series I. Audiencia de Guatemala. Subseries A. Microfilm
    This microfilm consists of images of approximately 70,000 pages of documents (129 microfilm rolls) for the first one hundred years after the conquest in 1524. Microfilm reels are housed with the rest of the APS microfilm, as Film #1337.
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 7, 5.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Peticiones, memoriales y otros documentos sueltos, anos 1584 a 1700. En este legajo hay solo dos documentos para el siglo XVI en Guatemala: dos cartas uns de 1584 con dos folios y otra de 1593 con un folio.
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 8, 10.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 2)
      Cartas y escrituras a S.M. en la provincia de Honduras desde el ano de 1549 hasta el de 1570. Destacan por su interes en relacion con la provincia de Guatemala, sede de la Audiencia, tres cartas: dos del obispo de Honduras (1550) y otra del provincial del Santo Domingo en Yucatan (1553).
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 9, 796.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 3)
      Cartas y expedientes del Presidente y oidores de dicha Audiencia. Anos de 1529-1573. a) Cartas de los miembros del gobierno de la Audiencia dando relacion del estado de ella en general o contestando al rey preguntas y consultas. b) Cartas del presidente, oidores y particulares pidiendo merced. c) Cartas con relacion de visitas efectuadas por funcionarios reales. d) Cartas de Alvarado y Montejo.
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 10, 809.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 4)
      Cartas y expedientes del Presidente y oidores de dicha Audiencia. Anos de 1574-1597. Este legajo contiene: a) Cartas, autos, cedulas, etc. sobre los ataques de los corsarios (Drake) y la defensa que se hizo de la costa. b) Cartas de la Real Audiencia dando noticias de todos los pueblos dependientes de ella sobre diversos asuntos: indios, tributos, evangelizacion, minas, cuentas de la Real Audiencia. c) Copias de Reales Cedulas dirigidas a la Audiencia. The substance of the document pertains to Guatemala.
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 10, 576.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 5)
      IDEM # 4
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 11, 156.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 6)
      Cartas y expedientes del presidente y oidores de esta Audiencia. Anos 1598-1603.
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 39, 210.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 7)
      Cartas y expedientes de los gobernadores de Costa Rica y Honduras, divididos en dos numeros. Costas Rica: anos de 1566 a 1680. Honduras: ano de 1526 a 1699. De la gobernacion de Guatemala, o referidos a ella, destacan los siguientes documentos: a) Descripcion de los corregimientos que ha de haber en la Gobernacion de Guatemala (sin ano); b) Cartas de el gobernador de Honduras y particulares contra el Presidente de la Audiencia (1577-1580-1609-1587-1606-1593-1595-1582); c) Cartas de Gobernador de Honduras y particulares sobre transporte y mercaderes (1591-1611-1609-1542-1585-1611); y d) Carta del Adelanto Montejo sobre la pacificacion de los indios (1539).
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 40, 40.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 8)
      Cartas y expedientes de los gobernadores de Soconusco y Nicaragua divididos en dos numeros. Soconusco: ano de 1565 a 1686. Nicaragua: ano de 1536 a 1692. Con referencia de Guatemala, descatan tres cartas de Gobernador de Nicaragua al rey contra la actuacion de la Audiencia (1582-1583-1584).
    - AGI Classification: Audiencia de Guatemala 41, 552.0 Photograph(s) (Microfiche 1337, Reel 9)